Good evening everybody today's דף daf is דף י"א. daf Yud Aleph.
I'm a bit ahead I understand which is great.
I thought we did the story about אונקלוס. Onkelos. Yeah so that
gets us a good way into the דף. daf.
So you know obviously it needs to be mentioned I mean it
sort of jumps off us the page but you know this whole
tractate of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah right is opening up this whole
question about how we think about the larger world and as I
mentioned is it about idolatry is it about a different type of
life a life that's not about תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvos and
so on. And then we get to the fact that like okay
but the Rabbis are sort of obviously aware of the world in
which they live they know all of these pagan holidays more than
that the whole calendar is structured around events of the larger world
the מניין שטרות Minyan Shtarot not the destruction of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and not you know the world the creation of the
world the socio-like structures of time. The idea of structuring time even
came up because it spoke about counting from תשרי Tishrei and not
from ניסן Nissan you know it's almost like a year that begins
in January rather than begins on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So you
know so like we're intimately you know sort of you know sort
of one fabric with that larger world even as we work to
retain our distinctiveness. And then the discussions yesterday they were actually you
know even like a little humorous but about how you know even
like you know אנטונינוס Antoninus which is a question exactly who that
is that's not Marc Antony the the dates don't work but anyway
Keafter has a very long note of it trying to identify exactly
which Caesar it is that we're talking about. But anyway the story
about how the the great Roman Caesar you know has this close
friendship with רבי. Rebbe. Now that might be built on a little
bit of fact in the sense that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda
HaNasi part of his role the role of the נשיאים Nesi'im in
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was to have a positive relationship with Rome.
So it's possible that there was some you know sort of connection
there. But the idea that they have this intimate friendship and that
you know אנטונינוס Antoninus is sneaking away from Rome each night and
going through a a secret cave or however measured out the distance
and you'd have to probably like do what like go like under
the Mediterranean or something like that anyway you know in order to
like have these private meetings with רבי Rebbe and then in the
middle like he sort of serves as a footstool for רבי. Rebbe.
So obviously you know that's quite I mean it's it's pretty humorous
to read that but it's a very powerful story about the Rabbis
you know because you have to think about who their audience is
right the audience is their fellow Jews who are feeling like you
know what does it mean to be minority to be oppressed to
be defenseless that you know you know like feeling like do you
really have faith in the tradition that you represent you know especially
given how the whole world seems to be all about the success
of Rome and everything and you know so even when you're not
being oppressed but it's just you know it's like why why do
you as a small little you know insignificant Jewish nation you know
you know like matter.
So you know and then these stories you know are very powerful
in sort of you know we remember the stories even as we
sort of know how absurd they are I guess I question how
much did the people at the time you know know that they
were you know not not factual or not but it's still inspirational
it's like oh you know you sort of the message comes in
even as you know it's not really true you know it's like
oh even they really recognize you know that they're just serving us
and like even that whole story about like their that public event
that they did every seventy years with עשו Esav and יעקב Yaakov
which is like the reverse right but that's like okay that's the
message you're always getting this event about how they're mocking the Jews
and they're supreme and we're you know whatever but the punchline is
is like is that at the end of that great event they
say oh but woe to us when ultimately you know when Jacob
is supreme right that was that last line of that event right
do you remember that after you know the whole thing I'm talking
about right the lame person and whatever and it says like you
know in the end of that thing was what was the end
of that line whatever it
was what oh
oh but I'm getting you know
oh I'm sorry I'm sorry that's the end of today's דף daf
I'm getting way ahead okay now I ruined the surprise anyway the
point being you'll see it the point being that like you know
that that here's how you can like even they deep down know
that we have the תורה Torah we're
supreme etc. etc. you know sort of like how the the what
was it the Romans needed us in order to beat the Greeks
remember that from before anyway so it's sort of
like Nuremberg saying it's פורים Purim
oh yeah there you go exactly. So anyway so I think you
know what this is doing in order to sort of frame an
a way of having pride and understanding of you know your role
within the world anyway we should obviously appreciate that that's part of
what's you know going on here or it is what's going on
here anyway okay so let's take a look oh one last thing
I want to mention before we turn before we actually get started
this tiny little תוספות Tosfos on דף י' עמוד ב' daf Yud
Amud Beis כל נשיאיה Kol Nesi'eha has in like six lines a
distilled version of because you know we talked about
which is not Josephus. It was a Hebrew pseudo-Josephus
written and people believed it to be a translation of Josephus. It
was very popular in the Middle Ages, I don't know, written in
the Middle Ages. Anyway, it's ספר יוסיפון. Sefer Josippon. So anyway he
quotes here in this whole תוספות, Tosafos, כל נשיאיה, Kol Nesi'eha, he
says the following: דאמר רי... Da'amar Ri... okay, שמפורש בספר יוסיפון, Shemeforash
beSefer Josippon, שנישבו רומיים, Shenishbu Romiyim,
כל נשיאיה, Kol Nesi'eha, about six lines into it, שנישבו רומיים שלא
להמליך עליהם עוד מלך, Shenishbu Romiyim shelo lehamlich aleihem od melech, the
Romans made an oath to never have another king, right? בשביל אחד
שלקח אשה אחת בחזקה, Bishvil echad shelakach isha achas bechazaka, because of
a case of a woman that was taken and raped, the rape
of the Sabines. Anybody heard that story? And that from that point
on, right, Rome decided that they could never have a king, that
they would never have a king.
אלא שהיו ממנים ישיש אחד, Ela shehayu memanim yashish echad, one ruler,
or not ruler, because actually what was the name before the period
of the Caesars? Do you know who was the head of the
Senate? What was it called? The person, the consuls.
Right. They continued to have them during the empire.
I know, I know. Anyway, one consul, right, ישיש yashish is not
even a
ruler because he didn't have that type of power. ולא שלש מאות
יועצים, Velo shelosh me'os yo'atzim, and he had three hundred advisors which
is really the Senate, okay, three hundred is just a big number.
וסוף כמה שנים מלך עליהם אחד בחזקה, Vesof kama shanim malach aleihem
echad bechazaka, but after a couple many years, right, one of them
actually
ruled over them
with,
anyway,
imposed his power over them, became a real force. Thank you, I
can't believe what happened to my head. It's funny. Ruled over them
with force, okay. שמתה אמו בלדתה ונבקע בטנה, Shemesa imo belidta venivka
bitna, right?
What was that? He had actually, he was born through cesarean section,
named after Caesar, okay. ומצאוהו חי ומלך עליהם, Umetzauhu chai umalach aleihem,
and he ultimately, I don't know what his... maybe a miraculous birth
type of story. But anyway, but that is the idea that Caesar
was born through a C-section, through a cesarean section. And anyway, so
this is skipping out the whole rest of his life, of all
the wars that he won that led to him
ultimately taking over the Senate. But anyway, so this one person ruled
over them with force. ונקרא קיסר בלשון רומי בלשון כרות בעברית, Venikra
Keisar belashon Romi belashon karus beIvris, and he was the first Caesar
in the language of Rome, in the language of 'cut' in Hebrew.
ועל שמו נקראו כל המלכים שאחריו קיסר, Ve'al shemo nikre'u kol hamelachim
she'achirav Keisar, and after him that's why all the later rulers were
called Caesars. So there you go, beautiful little distillation of Roman history
in like six lines. Anyway, all right.
So... the first one? What? The born cesarean section according to...
I think so. Yeah. Anyway, all right.
So now anyway, and that actually is close to what actually happened.
Right, exactly. Okay, so anyway, we had the whole story there about
how אנטונינוס Antoninus sort of
recognizes the greatness of רבי Rebbi and so on. And then we
had the whole story about at the beginning of yesterday, top of
יא עמוד א, Yud Aleph Amud Aleph, you got a little ahead
about אונקלוס הגר, Onkelos HaGer, which is a sort of similar story,
that even the non-Jews recognize this great person, recognizes us and converted.
And then even when all these officers were sent, all he had
to do was give them a little glimmer of the truth, of
the true path, and all of a sudden they convert. So obviously
this is sort of making us appreciate that even in our sort
of minority and oppressed status, the power of the faith that we
believe in. I do think by the way that Jews in the
Roman world
were much more significant percentage of the population than we are today
in the world population. Like I don't know exactly how that happened,
but that our
relative... I don't know, something like twenty million or something. Cale, you
probably know?
Well, that wasn't what I was going to ask about, but it
was much higher. Yeah. Persecutions and conversions.
Yeah, I'm not sure, or assimilation. Yeah.
So two things: one is, what we had yesterday about
the son succeeding the father, that had already happened. Titus was the
son of Vespasian. Right, right. And that seems to be ignored here.
Yeah, what can I tell you?
And the second thing is the Roman emperors were not styled as
kings until long after Rebbi was gone. It was the late third
century.
Oh, you mean because he used the phrase king yesterday? Yeah, but
that was the גמרא Gemara like translating it into its own terms.
But that's true. These histories actually... I don't know. Okay, anyway the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, now we pick up now four
lines, five lines from the bottom from before the lines get wide
on יא עמוד א. Yud Aleph Amud Aleph.
Okay.
ויאמר ה' לו, Vayomer Hashem lo, so God says now to רבקה,
Rivka, thank you. שני גוים בבטנך, Shnei goyim bevitnech, two nations in
your womb. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב אל תקרי גוים אלא גאים,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav al tikri goyim ela ge'im, haughty ones
or not haughty, whatever, ones of great stature. דאנטונינוס ורבי, DeAntoninus veRebbi,
this refers to Antoninus and Rebbi. So of course here the whole
story about... Go back to Rivka, thank you, שני גוים בבטנך, Shnei
goyim bevitnecha, two nations in your womb. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב,
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, אל תקרי גוים, al tikrei goyim, nations,
but אלא גיים, ela geyyim, haughty ones or not haughty, whatever, you
know, like ones of great stature. ואנטונינוס ורבי, Ve'Antoninos ve'Rabbi, this refers
to Antoninos and Rabbi. So of course here's the whole story about,
this is a different theme, but about how we sort of read
world events, you know, Yosef Yerushalmi in his little book זכור, Zachor,
if you haven't read it, you must read it. It's a tiny
little book, but it's very, you know, it's foundational. Anyway, it talks
about how Jews did, like, did not do history, they did memory.
So obviously, you know, they were not about necessarily like being interested
in finding out the facts for their own sakes, but it was
about a sense of Jewish memory and how we interpret history and
what sort of, you know, how it shapes our way of looking
at the world and how all past events are read through sort
of the biblical lens and are put into, like, every anti-semite is
a המן, Haman, every story, like, things sort of are fit into
this paradigm or this... anyway, you know, this like archetype, and that
makes sense of our past, and it also gives us a sense
of confidence, bad things will happen but ultimately God will save us
and we'll survive, you know, it becomes the lens through which we
read history. So, if you think about it, right, in the תורה,
Torah, the big sort of
warring entities, you know, that fought against, I mean obviously Pharaoh, you
know, sort of subjugated the Jews, enslaved the Jews, the Israelites, but
the sense of like, you know, this model of like the two
entities that are constantly striving against one another is יעקב Yaakov and
עשו. Esav. But of course, that doesn't translate in a post-biblical period
because עשו Esav becomes אדום Edom and אדום Edom becomes this ancient
nation that dies out. So then, if you're looking at who is
that model for to represent sort of the outsiders there, the non-Jews
that are our, you know, sort of constantly warring against us, then
אדום Edom becomes translated as Rome.
And I don't know exactly even how they try to connect the
dots or if they tried to connect the dots, but it was
just taken for granted that עשו Esav is אדום Edom is Rome.
And then after Rome stops existing, you know, then it becomes Judaism
and Christianity. And that was helped by the fact that of course
that you know the Holy Roman Empire and that Rome adopted Christianity
as its religion. So all of these issues about you know Jews
versus the Romans or Jews and Judaism and Christianity is all read
through a יעקב Yaakov עשו Esav type of a lens. Okay, so
here though, you're sort of reading the one time in which they
got along together. Okay, so שני גוים בבטנך, Shnei goyim bevitnecha, these
are these two great ones, the great Jew and the great Roman,
זה אנטונינוס ורבי, Zeh Antoninos ve'Rabbi, שלא פסק מעל שלחנם לא חזרת
ולא קשות ולא צנון. shelo pasak me'al shulchanam lo chazeret velo kishut
velo tzenon.
They were, they didn't have, they were so wealthy that they had
even these vegetables out of season, which we totally take for granted
that we expect all vegetables all times of the year, but you
know, that was of course obviously not true in the ancient world,
and they had these amazing vegetables,
they never ceased neither lettuce, nor cucumbers, nor radishes, לא בימי החמה
ולא בימי הגשמים, lo biyemei hachama velo biyemei hageshamim, whether in the
summer time or the winter time, they always had these. דאמר מר,
De'amar mar, צנון מחתך אוכל, tzenon mechatech ochel,
radishes help chop up the food in your stomach, digest the food,
חזרת מהפך מאכל, chazeret mehappech ma'achal,
the lettuce in your stomach helps sort of churn it around, you
know, all these are good for digestion, קשות מרחיב מעיים, kishut marchiv
mei'ayim,
and the cucumbers help expand your stomach. תוספות Tosafot says part of
the point here was not just that they had vegetables at off-season,
but that they had the types of vegetables that were necessary for
good digestion because their tables were so, you know, overflowing with all
different types of foods and delicacies. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
says ותניא דבי רבי ישמעאל למה נקרא שמם קשואין מפני שקשין לגופו
של אדם, Ve'atanyah devei Rabbi Yishmael lama nikre sheman kishu'in mipnei shekashin
legufo shel adam, but don't we say that they're called קשואין kishu'in
like gourd or whatever cucumbers because they're hard, bad for your body,
כחרבות kecharavot like swords? So לא קשיא הא ברברבי והא בזוזי, lo
kashya, ha berabbeyei ve'ha bezozei, it depends whether you have big cucumbers
or small
ones, presumably I guess the big ones are not good. Yes, Michael,
what do you want to say?
No, no, just a small passing comment that I remember reading even
yesterday in the זהר Zohar that צנאן tsnon was with an alef.
Right, he picked up the צנון, tsnon, oh, right. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this, יום לידה ויום מיתה, yom leida
ve'yom mita, so continuing back with the holidays of the Romans,
the day of birth and the day of death. Anyway, more, the
point here is, and actually here we get to an interesting halakhic,
very important halakhic discussion. The גמרא Gemara says that רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says the only day that the problem is a death day
that includes with it
a pyre, a funeral pyre, but one that is not associated with
a funeral pyre is not a pagan holiday, okay, and the rabbis
don't distinguish. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, מכלל דרבי מאיר
סבר, miklal de'Rabbi Meir savar, from this we can infer that רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir holds לא שנא מיתה שיש בה שריפה ולא שנא
מיתה שאין בה שריפה פלחי לה לעבודת כוכבים, lo shena mita sheyesh
bah sereifa velo shena mita she'ein bah sereifa, pachi lah la'avodat kochavim,
that
you know, whether they're having a funeral pyre or not, at funerals
they do some form of pagan worship. Okay, אלמא שריפה לאו חקה
היא, alma sereifa lav chuka hi,
so obviously the funeral pyre is not a חקה, chuka, חקה chuka
is invoked in the verse בחקתיהם לא תלכו, bechukoteihem lo telechu, don't
go in their paths. but here has the specific meaning of like
a pagan type of a ritual. So, you know, he says like,
with or without the fire, it's funny, I mean the fire could
be a pagan ritual but you could do pagan worship with or
without it, but anyway, don't give too much weight to the funeral
pyre, that's not significant, these are pagan days where pagan worship regardless.
Okay. מכלל Michlal from that we can infer דרבנן סברי שריפה חוקה
היא derabbanan savri s'reifa chuka hi that the rabbis say no, only
funerals with these pyres, funeral pyres, so presumably for them the funeral
pyre is a type of a pagan rite, and only when you
have that pagan ritual is there pagan worship, okay, and otherwise it
is not a problem, that's not a pagan holiday. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this, והנן v'hanan but we learn in a ברייתא
braita שורפין על המלכים ולא מדרכי האמורי. sorfin al hamlachim v'lo midarchei
ha'emori. Actually,
even for a case of a Jewish king, you can have a
funeral pyre, not burning the body but, you know, burning, maybe, maybe
I shouldn't be using the word funeral pyre, maybe that's the simply
refers to burning the body, I don't know, but anyway, you can
have
the, like cremation,
yeah, yeah, right, right, but it was done as a, as a
ritual, not just as a way of processing the body, but anyway,
but you know, שורפין על המלכים sorfin al hamlachim means you burn,
we'll see in a minute, you burn their like personal, personal effects
and other types of things, so you can do this, apparently, this
was a ritual that was done particularly when great people died and
even the Jews have adopted it and they would do it for
their kings, okay, or you know, so, and the משנה mishna says
that that is not considered דרכי האמורי, darchei emori, ways of the
Amorite, which is interesting where the גמרא Gemara got that phrase from,
but that's another way of saying like בחוקותיהם. bechukoteihem. It's not considered
a pagan type of a ritual. You know, things, it's weird, they
do it in the larger society, it doesn't really have any rational
explanation or whatever, you know, but it's not a prohibition of going
in their ways and בחוקותיהם bechukoteihem because it's not really a pagan
ritual. So that's what the ברייתא braita says there in שבת. Shabbat.
Like אין משתמשין בשרביטו של מלך, ein mishtamshin besharvito shel melech, right?
Yeah, but that's not, but that might be, but that wouldn't require
this ritual. This has a particular ritual, okay. Not everything that is
a ritual is a בחוקותיהם, bechukoteihem, is a pagan ritual, right? Thanksgiving
is a ritual, right? Having the turkey, having the this, having the,
you know, the cranberry sauce. We ritualize it, but that doesn't make
it a
pagan, okay. So אין בו משום דרכי
האמורי. Ein bo mishum darchei emori. ואי חוקה היא, v'ei chuka hi,
but if it really is a חוק chok היא, hi, אנן היכי
שרפינן, anan heichi sarfinan, how can we do it? והכתיב ובחוקותיהם לא
תלכו, vehaktiv uvchukoteihem lo telechu, and it's written, you're not supposed to
go in their ways. So, so how do you explain this? It
seems from this ברייתא braita that it is not a pagan ritual.
אלא דכולי עלמא שריפה לאו חוקה היא. Ela dechulei alma s'reifa lav
chuka hi. Fine, everybody agrees it's not per se a pagan ritual.
אלא חשיבותא היא, Ela chashivuta hi,
but what it is is, it's a signal for a very important
funeral, right? You only do this when it's the death of a
really important person or when the event itself, it gives tremendous weight
to the event. It's not itself a form of pagan worship or
a pagan ritual, but it signals a death of and or a
funeral of a very important person, a very important funeral, which is
why we can do it. We can also signal that. So there's
what the גמרא Gemara is going to say is it correlates, it's
not, it's not the same but it correlates to pagan worship. When
we do it, there's no pagan worship and it's not a pagan
ritual, okay, but when they do it, חשיבותא היא, chashivuta hi, where
I lost my place, והכא בהא קא מיפלגי. vehacha beha ka mipleigi.
This is the debate. ר' מאיר סבר לא שנא מיתה שיש בה
שריפה ולא שנא מיתה שאין בה שריפה פלחי לה לעבודת כוכבים. Rabbi
Meir savar lo shena mita she-yesh bah s'reifa v'lo shena mita she-ein
bah s'reifa palchei leh le-avodat kochavim. You know, those pagans, they worship
idolatry, they worship, they'll do their pagan worship at all funerals, whether
it's an important one or a not important one, there's always some
pagan worship going on and therefore it's a problem about, you know,
worship, about doing business with them on their pagan holiday. ורבנן סברי,
V'rabbanan savri, and the rabbis hold, מיתה שיש בה שריפה חשיבא להו
ופלחי בה. mita she-yesh bah s'reifa chashiva lehu u-falchei bah. This is
a sign of what type of a day it is, it's not
the problem itself. If they're doing this whole funeral pyre and this
whole thing, you know that this is a big deal funeral, and
at big deal funerals you know that part of that consists of
pagan worship. The actual fire itself is not a pagan worship and
is not a pagan ritual, but it comes together with it, okay,
and therefore if they're having this, you know there's pagan worship going
on, okay, ושאין בה שריפה לא חשיבא ולא פלחי, ve-she-ein bah s'reifa
lo chashiva v'lo palchei, but if it's not doing this, then it's
not an important funeral and they won't do it. But we can
actually do the ritual that takes place during their funerals that have
pagan worship because the ritual itself is not an actually about pagan
worship or is not per se a pagan ritual, okay. It's like
you said, you know, well, whenever they're wearing, I don't know, their
tuxedos or something, you know, then you know that they're going to
be doing some form of, of, you know, of pagan ritual at
their wedding. Okay, but when nobody bothers with their tuxedos, it's casual
dress, they won't do it. So that doesn't mean it's אסור ossur
for us to wear tuxedos, it has nothing to do with the
pagan worship itself. Yes, Charlie.
Yeah, so the, the Queen's birthday is still a holiday in most
of the British Empire former... Okay.
...and the funeral of the last King, which is before I think
most of us were born, was actually a really big deal.
Okay, there you go. All right, so
now, yeah. Well, they are going to burn animals. We're going to
see about that.
Doesn't it get to a point where it becomes like uncomfortable, it
gets like too close to looking like עבודה זרה avoda zara, *Avodah
Zarah*?
Apparently the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is not concerned about that. I mean,
maybe there would be some cases, yes, but in general it wasn't
concerned. Now, there is an important discussion in general about the boundaries
of בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*, because this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to closely connect
בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* to something that is pagan related—meaning not just secular society,
not just, you know, but actually connected with some form of עבודה
זרה Avodah Zorah *Avodah Zarah*, some form of pagan worship. תוספות Tosafot
*Tosafot* is bothered because in another גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it seems like,
like בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* could have a larger scope, like it spoke, if
you remember in סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, about is executing by, you know, by
the sword a type of a בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*? And then, and then
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also says that if things are written in
the תורה Torah *Torah*, you know, then it's not a problem of
בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*. And the burning of the kings we're going to actually
see in a minute is based on a פסוק *Pasuk*, well not
in the תורה Torah *Torah* but in נ״ך *Nach*, where it speaks
about how Jewish kings, you know, they had these burnings. So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* says what's the story? So תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* actually lines
these things together and he says בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* encompasses two categories.
One: things that are really associated with other religions or with עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah, *Avodah Zarah*, and those things, it doesn't matter if,
you know, there's some parallel in the תורה Torah *Torah* or whatever,
once they're really associated with these other religions, they remain off limits.
Other things are just weird, arbitrary practices that they have, like the
executing by a sword or whatever it might be. And he says
in those, if, you know, we have our own history with those
things and they're in the תורה Torah *Torah*, then it's okay. Anyway,
the point ultimately being though that בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*, this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
makes it sound like בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* is specifically things associated with עבודה
זרה avodah zarah, *Avodah Zarah*. And while that is the sort of
prime category of בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*, there's other גמרות *Gemaros* that make it
sound like there are times where that could include other forms of,
of practices of the larger society, although not as off limits and
easier to sort of say, well, we're not really getting it from
them, it's not really totally taboo, if we have a basis for
it ourselves we can do it, and so on. But, you know,
at least the discussion of בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* relates to those things as
well.
Sorry, but how do you know which one of those things it
would be? You know what I mean?
You don't. Whatever. There's a whole discussion in the פוסקים *Poskim*. I'm
not giving a whole שיעור shiur *Shiur* on בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*. What I'm
trying to though say is I think actually, and it's funny that
בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* is not a more central discussion here in עבודה זרה
avoda zara *Avodah Zarah*, because if you think about it—and I've written
about this—that,
that the real question about how much do we integrate or not
integrate with the larger society, meaning how much is it about separateness
or, or about distinctiveness? Right? We can sort of, you know, dress
like them and go, you know, and look very similar in all
those things and still do certain things that retain our distinctiveness. Or
we can try to, like, cloister ourselves, build up walls, remain totally
separate. And to some degree the question of the scope of בחוקותיהם
*Bechukoteihem* is a, you know, is exactly that question. If בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem*
just says don't do things that are like pagan related, okay, fine.
Doesn't mean that I can't go ahead and look normal and, you
know, live among them and, you know, similar types of ways of
life and practices. Just don't do certain things that are really taboo,
that are really like problematic. Okay? Whereas if בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* means like,
no, like, you know, even normal neutral practices I have to, you
know, be really, you know, separate myself from, you know, then that
really is not just about distinctiveness, that's really about, you know, separating
off. So anyway, so I think that the בחוקותיהם *Bechukoteihem* is a
big thing in this larger conversation about our place within, you know,
our relationship to the larger society. So here we get it in
passing, but it's a larger discussion. Yeah.
Right. I mean, again, you know, because I guess maybe ultimately you
can't reconcile all the different teachings. Because you have the whole לא
שינו את שמם ומלבושם ולשונם *lo shinu et shemam umalbusham uleshonam* which
then would say that like, you know, this, it's a much, you
know what I mean? Anything is a problem.
Yeah, I wrote about that also. רב משה *Rav Moshe* in a
תשובה *Teshuvah*, I'm just going to say one last thing because we're
off topic. רב משה *Rav Moshe* in a תשובה *Teshuvah* says that—or
he says, you know—all these, if somebody asked רב משה *Rav Moshe*,
should it be אסור assur *assur* to give secular names? And he
says what are you talking about? All these great rabbis in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* had secular names and, and you know, all great
rabbis throughout time, not all of them, but many of them had
secular names. And רב משה *Rav Moshe* says this whole thing of
לא שינו שמם ומלבושם ולשונם *lo shinu shemam umalbusham uleshonam*... he says
first of all, okay, it's good to have a Jewish name, it's
not ideal to have a non-Jewish name. But then he says לא
שינו שמם ומלבושם ולשונם *lo shinu shemam umalbusham uleshonam*, he says that's
when there wasn't yet any מצוות *Mitzvos*. So that there wasn't anything
to distinguish them, so you needed these sort of more external signs,
you know, to, to create a sense of distinctiveness. Now that we
have the מצוות *Mitzvos*, he says, you don't have to be so
מקפיד *makpid* on all this stuff. Okay, which is really, I mean,
look, it speaks to a lot about the difference of Modern Orthodoxy
and חרדי *Haredi* Judaism. But we are getting off topic. So back
to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. Yeah, it's very interesting. You could read
what I've written on it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like
this: גופא *Gufa*, שורפין על המלכים ואין בה משום דרכי האמורי darchei
ha'emori, *Sorefin al hamelachim ve-ein bah mishum darchei ha-emori*. Let's go back
to that teaching. You can do these burnings over the death of
kings and it's not considered to be a pagan practice, a way
of the Amorite. שנאמר *Shene'emar*, and here's the פסוק *Pasuk* that supports
it: בשלום תמות *Beshalom tamut*. This is a פסוק *Pasuk* that is
said by—who is this? חזקיהו *Chizkiyahu* I think? Yeah, no, צדקיהו Tzidkiyahu;
*Tzidkiyahu*, excuse me, צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*. בשלום תמות *Beshalom tamut*, you will die...
and peace and ובמשרפות אבותיך המלכים אשר שרפו לפניך and you will
have a similar type of a burning of the kings that was
done, you know, with your forefathers. So it wasn't only done with
צדקיהו; it was done with like all these kings, and the תורה
Torah is totally okay with it. וכשם ששורפין על המלכים כך שורפין
על הנשיאים; U'keshem shesorfin al melachim kach sorfin al nesieem; and it
wouldn't only be for kings, it would also be for נשיאים, nesieem,
meaning, presumably meaning like with what רבי, Rebbe, who we just got
through talking about, רבי Rebbe and Antoninus and so on, you know,
when רבי Rebbe would die and when his children would die or
whatever, they would presumably do this type of a thing. ומהי
הם שורפין? U'mahi hem sorfin? And what would they burn? So not
the body itself but מטתן וכלי תשמישן, mitatan u'chlei tashmishan, their beds.
Now, their beds doesn't necessarily mean their beds from their bedrooms; it
could mean their funeral biers, you know, the sort of the plank
in which they took the body out of the city to bury.
Maybe it means their beds, because the next line is וכלי תשמישן,
u'chlei tashmishan, their personal effects. So maybe bed does literally mean bed.
ומעשה שמת רבן גמליאל הזקן, U'ma'aseh shemet Rabban Gamliel hazaken, here's רבן
גמליאל הזקן, Rabban Gamliel hazaken, because we just said they would do
it for the נשיאים, nesieem, okay? So רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel the
elder died, ושרף עליו אונקלוס הגר, ve'saraf alav Onkelos hager, he saw
all—all the threads are tied back together, we have אונקלוס—שבעים מנה mana
צורי,
70 מנה of Tyre, which is—was an enormous amount of money, but
it sounds like he actually burnt the money. So the גמרא Gemara
says, והא מהי הם שורפין עליו מטתן וכלי תשמישן? ve'ha mai hem
sorfin alav mitatan u'chlei tashmishan? But you just got through saying that
they only burn their personal effects. No, אימא בשבעים מנה צורי. eima
b'shivim mana tzuri. No, that was the cost of the personal effects.
It's also interesting that אונקלוס הגר Onkelos hager is doing it, because
in the whole point that, oh, it's not pagan, and we actually
get it from the פסוקים, pesukim, the person who's making a big
deal about it is the person who is coming from this outside
culture who is now, you know, converted in. So one wonders if
it wasn't אונקלוס הגר, Onkelos hager, somebody else would have maybe done
as much. Maybe say, you know, אדרבה, adiraba, he understood that, you
know, you have to make a, you know, you have to make
a big deal about it. Why should רבי Rebbe be treated differently
than a Roman emperor? Yes.
This also puts אונקלוס הגר Onkelos hager pretty early in the Tannaitic
period.
Well, yeah, that's true. The גמרא Gemara says that אונקלוס Onkelos was—and
the whole question of whether all the stories about אונקלוס הגר, Onkelos
hager, first of all, there's also a known עקילס, Aquilas, and is
that the same as אונקלוס Onkelos and all these historical questions about
how it matches up. But I think the גמרא Gemara says that
אונקלוס Onkelos was a student of רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and רבי
יהושע, Rebbe Yehoshua, which would put in the same time, if I'm
remembering correctly, of רבי עקיבא, Rebbe Akiva, which would be 130, and
רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel was when?
רבן גמליאל הזקן Rabban Gamliel hazaken was before that, long before the
destruction of the Temple.
Oh, that's true. It's the other רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel that's later.
Yeah, yeah, that's, that's weird. I'll have to see maybe whether the
text, all of the texts have—maybe there're texts that don't have הזקן
hazaken in it. I'll have to see. Anyway, okay, ואמרת מאי, ve'amarta
mai, as we just did that, okay. ומידי אחריני לא? U'midai achrinei
lo? Is it true that you really wouldn't burn other types of
things other than personal effects? והתניא, Ve'hatanya, we learned a ברייתא: baraita:
עוקרין על המלכים ואין בו משום דרכי אמורי, okin al hamelachim ve'ein
bo mishum darchei emori, that you would actually hobble a horse as
part of, presumably also, the funeral of a king. עוקרין Okin presumably
means like you would cut their
tendons of their legs, and it's not considered an Amorite process. Now,
you could say that's not burning, that's just, that's a different type
of, you know, destructive type of thing to do. You know, presumably
it's a way of showing like how tragic the death is, you
know, same like, you know, we do it, sort of, we do
קריעה, keriah, you know, oh my god, you know, it's tragic, you
know, and like my world is destroyed and, you know, things are
broken. Of course the תורה Torah puts a limit to it, you
know, you don't make incisions in the flesh, right? You know, you
don't do it like, you know, obviously symbolically incisions in the flesh
is like a part of my very body is being ripped away,
this hurts me, you know, so deep or whatever. But the תורה
Torah says no, you know, that it, you can't go that far.
That would be either idolatrous or not respectful of the body or
going too far. So it's interesting that these types of things are
like midpoint between קריעה keriah on your garments and incisions on the
flesh, like it's really destructive but it's still on external objects. Okay,
but anyway this isn't exactly burning, so the גמרא Gemara could have
said maybe there's a difference; when we talked about personal effects it
was only burning, you would do this for other types of, you
know, other things for other objects. But the גמרא Gemara. wants to
understand that all of this is connected to personal effects. Maybe it—the—wants
to think it doesn't get too out of hand. Okay, so how
do you explain what's done to the horses? So the גמרא Gemara
says סוס שרכב עליו, sus sherachav alav, it is his personal effect,
it's like his car, it's the horse that he used. ובהמה טהורה
לא? U'vehemah tehorah lo? Are you telling me you wouldn't do it
for just, you know, kosher animals which were not personal effects? והתניא,
Ve'hatanya, we learned a ברייתא: baraita: עיקור שיש בו טריפה אסור שאין
בו טריפה מותר. ikur sheyesh bo tereifah asur she'ein bo tereifah mutar.
If they did afterwards—since they didn't actually kill the horses—if they actually
just did this, this hobbling, if they hobbled it in a way
that it made it a טריפה, tereifah, you can't eat it, which
is like, duh. But if they hobbled it in a way that
didn't make it a טריפה, tereifah, you can eat it. And תוספות
Tosafot. says the חידוש chiddush is that don't think that because it
went through this type of a ritual and maybe it should be
like, you know, like the—since the whole thing
is like this belong to the king or the נשיא, nasi, maybe
this should sort of make it like forbidden to derive benefit, like
it's sort of puts it off limits, you know, the fact that
it went under this ritual. So the point is no, afterwards, the
things they burnt are burnt, but the things the—the horse, the animals
that they did this to. It wasn't a horse, it was a
cow, whatever, you could eat it if it's not a טרפה. treifa.
So איזהו eizehu עיקר ikar שם shem בטרפה betreifa and what types
of hobbling does not make it a טרפה treifa המנשר hamnasher
פרסותיו parsotav מן הארכובה ולמטה. min ha'arkuva u'lemata. If you basically cut
its tendons from the ankle down. Anyway, so you see that they
would do it to things that are not personal effects. So תרגמה
targema רב פפא Rav Pappa בעגלה המושכת בקרון. ba'agala hamoshechet bakaron. No,
it still would be his car, a different car, it would be
the calf or whatever that drew the wagon. Okay, so it still
be yes, could be a kosher animal that still is being used
some degree as his car and therefore but they would only do
it to personal effects. Okay, I want to read a brief תוספות
Tosafot. which is very important, a little off topic, but if you
turn back the page, yes, this
page just looks like the רי"ף Rif ראש Rosh and ר"ן Ran
many of the other ראשונים Rishonim do not have הזקן. Hazaken.
Oh, יישר כוח!
shkoach!
Alright, Jenna fixed the historical issue noted by Charlie,
that's why
we're okay, that the many of the other ראשונים Rishonim do not
have הזקן Hazaken which would put him רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel which
is right around the time of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right?
Right, and the תוספתא Tosefta does not have
it, so if it's not the תוספתא... Tosefta... Well, okay, we'll have
to check the... there are different manuscripts of the תוספתא. Tosefta. Who
notes that? What type of גמרא is that? Is that like the
ש"ס? Shas? What? Okay, excellent work by Jenna, יישר כוח. shkoach. Okay,
so now let's look also at the תוספות Tosafot עוקרין על המלכים.
okrin ala melachim. If you turn back to י"א ע"ב, yod aleph
amud bet, he says, ואי תימא ve'im toma דאמאי לא פריך de'amai
lo parich דאיכא צער בעלי חיים. de'ika tza'ar ba'alei chayim.
Forget this issue of דרכי האמורי, how are you allowed to do
this stuff, aren't you inflicting pain on animals? כי פריך לקמן ki
parich lekaman גבי נושא ונותן בשוק של עבודה זרה. gabbi noseh venoten
beshuk shel avoda zara. Okay,
we'll see that later. דאיכא משום בל תשחית? de'ika mishum bal tashchit?
Like have another question, isn't this בל תשחית? bal tashchit? You're destroying
all of this property. So he says, that doesn't bother me, says
תוספות. Tosafot כיון דלכבודו של מלך עושין כן אין כאן השחתה. keivan
delikhvodo shel melech osin ken ein kan hashchata. They're doing it to
honor the king, it's not considered wanton destruction. As opposed to what
your Jewish mother might have told you, it's very hard to transgress
בל תשחית. bal tashchit. Because בל תשחית bal tashchit means that it's
like wasteful wanton destruction. If it's serving some type of a purpose,
it's not בל תשחית. bal tashchit. So even if the purpose is
like a
symbolic type of a thing or an expression of grief or whatever,
it's not בל תשחית. bal tashchit. You're destroying it for a reason,
not just for the sake of destroying. So בל תשחית bal tashchit
doesn't bother me, says תוספות. Tosafot, But the animal is still suffering.
So what happened to צער בעלי חיים? tza'ar ba'alei chayim? Okay, אלא
הוה כמצחין שמיא מנא אלא צער בעלי חיים איחודא. ella hava kematzchin
shamya mana ella tza'ar ba'alei chayim ichuta. ויש לומר veyesh lomar says
תוספות Tosafot? דשאני כבוד המלך שהוא כבוד כל ישראל. deshani kvod hamelech
shehu kvod kol Yisrael.
When it comes to the honoring the king, you know, honor defined
by social norms, define what's considered acts of honor or not. So
to not in this in certain society to not do this would
be to not show honor,
and to do it is a way of showing honor and in
that context, so the honoring of the king is כבוד כל ישראל,
kvod kol Yisrael, if it's a Jewish king or a Jewish נשיא,
Nasi, it brings honor to the Jewish people. ואתי כבוד רבים ודחי
צער בעלי חיים. ve'ati kvod rabim vedachi tza'ar ba'alei chayim. And that
is a very important value as well, you know, the honor of
the Jewish people, the honor of the masses, and that comes and
that overrides צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. So yes, it is
a צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei chayim issue, but something else here,
you know, weighed against it. Now this תוספות Tosafot is also very
important because if I ask you according to תוספות, Tosafot do you
think it is permissible to inflict pain on animals for the sake
of human benefit? Let's say I want to, you know, I don't
know, do animal experimentation to make Mary Kay cosmetics for example. Okay,
everybody.
I know, whatever, exactly.
Okay, do you think that that is permissible if animals actually suffer
according to תוספות? Tosafot... Does he say animal suffering is permissible for
the sake of human benefit? What do you think? The תוספות Tosafot.
we just read.
Did he? What? Yes and no. Partly.
Well,
some people think yes, but no, he seemed to say that it's
a very special case. It's a case of כבוד הרבים, kvod harabim,
right? It's not any human benefit. כבוד הרבים kvod harabim is like
a value that we have other places, like we say כבוד הבריות,
kvod habriyot, you know, trumps certain issues, certainly כבוד הרבים kvod harabim
trumps certain issues. So this תוספות Tosafot, actually seems to say this
is a very narrow permission. When you have something like כבוד הרבים,
kvod harabim, you know, that can override צער בעלי חיים tza'ar ba'alei
chayim because that's one תורה value against another תורה value. Okay, and
this one you have to decide between them. But you know, being
able to have nice cosmetics is not a תורה value. But there's
no sense in תוספות... Tosafot medicine maybe, if it actually... okay. So
things that really translate not just into I'd like to eat veal,
you know, but things that translate into real תורה values maybe you
could say then you have to decide which one is going to
win out. But just human benefit, no. But that's this תוספות. Tosafot
But other... another תוספות, Tosafos the... whatever... the פסקי תוספות Piskei Tosafot
in the back, and a number of ראשונים, Rishonim, the רמב"ן Ramban
and others, read it much broader. And they say anytime it serves
human benefit allows צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. And that's actually
the... the position that gets adopted להלכה. le'halacha. And that becomes very...
you know, on the one hand it means like, you know, questions
came up, can I go ahead and pluck feathers from... from geese?
geese for down. So if you take too restrictive of a position,
you're going to say, "Oh no, it doesn't matter, there's a tiny
little, it's a little painful for the animals" if you're too restrictive.
But if you're too permissive, then it's like we don't have to
care and we can go ahead and make veal and do all
this type of stuff and not care about the suffering of the
animals and not try to limit it or whatever. So it becomes
a really interesting question of where to draw the line and whether,
you know, just benefit as opposed to a value is enough to
allow צער בעלי חיים. tza'ar ba'alei chayim. Yes, Jenna.
And it goes with all these questions of the modern fashion industry
and how much is the benefit of making things cheaper and more
accessible outweigh against the, like, the צער? tza'ar? Exactly.
Right. And the people that are concerned about these issues about animal
welfare, it's very frustrating because, you know, הלכה halacha could in theory
have developed and created a
calculus. Here's x amount of benefit and x amount of pain, right?
And the amount of benefit has to justify somehow the amount of
pain. But it never created a calculus and we wound up ruling
against תוספות Tosafos and saying that benefit, any type of benefit, permits
צער בעלי חיים, tza'ar ba'alei chayim, but this תוספות Tosafos does not
hold of that. Okay, so let's continue. That was a total type
of digression but important one. Okay, י"א עמוד ב'. Yud Aleph amud
bet. יום תגלחת זקנו. Yom Tiklachat Zikno. This is why when I
give a שיעור shiur we fall behind and when other people give
the שיעור we get ahead. Okay, so the day of shaving of
the beard is another pagan holiday. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. They asked
the following question. היכי תני? Heichi tani? יום תגלחת זקנו והנחת בלוריתו?
Yom Tiklachat Zikno v'hanachat blurito?
So the בלורית blurit I get a sense is a type of
a ponytail. I don't know, I didn't really research it, but anyway,
is it the day of the shaving of the beard and when
he sort of, you know, sort of leaves the ponytail? Leaving his
lock of hair.
I know it's a lock of hair, but I'm just trying to...
I know leaving, I know leaving.
I'm just saying what a בלורית blurit is. I think it's a
type of a ponytail or some type of a lock of hair.
או יום תגלחת זקנו והעברת בלוריתו? O yom Tiklachat Zikno v'ha'avarat blurito?
Or maybe it's the day where you actually cut it off. It
sounds like רש"י Rashi said that they would grow it for a
year and then they would cut it off, you know, like these
people that grow their hair and then they cut it for to
give to Locks of Love or these types of things. Anyway, so
there would be a whole ritual.
Didn't אבשלום Avshalom have some... what? Was it אבשלום Avshalom who grew
his hair very long?
Yeah, אבשלום Avshalom grew it long. Right, but here... but
there was a regular shaving of the hair? No, he just grew
it very long, I think. Anyway, okay, so here they would have
a ritual when they would sort of maybe get it started, the
growing, like you know, and then they would have a ritual when
they would cut it off. So which one is the pagan day?
So of course, תא שמע דתניא תרוייהו. Tashma de-tanya travaihu. Both of
them. יום תגלחת זקנו והנחת בלוריתו. Yom Tiklachat Zikno v'hanachat blurito. One
ברייתא braita says when this lock of hair is sort of set
aside, you know, it's somehow prepared to be grown. ואידך אמר Ve-idach
amar יום תגלחת זקנו והעברת בלוריתו. Yom Tiklachat Zikno v'ha'avarat blurito. Fine,
so both of them. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda
amar Shmuel. עוד אחר יש להם. Od acher yesh lahem. Ah, this
is what I was jumping ahead. Ah, we have one pagan holiday
we forgot to mention and this is a big one. Okay, this
is all really about more also about Rome, the Romans versus the
Jews. ברומי. be-Romi. אחת לשבעים שנה. achat l'shiv'im shana. Only once every
seventy years. מביאים אדם שלם. Mevi'im adam shalem.
They bring a person who is like a full-bodied, like you know,
not... or we'll see it's contrasted to a person who's lame. ומרכיבין
אותו על אדם חיגר. U-markivin oto al adam chiger. And they have
somebody with like a lame or limp
representing יעקב Yaakov with the limp, okay? So and they have the
person who is like, you know, big and strong and healthy riding
on top of the man with the limp. So that's עשו Eisav
riding on top of יעקב. Yaakov. ומלבישין אותו בגדי אדם הראשון. U-malbishin
oto bigdei Adam Ha-Rishon.
And they dress the guy on the top with the clothes of
אדם הראשון. Adam Ha-Rishon. How the Romans got the clothes of אדם
הראשון? Adam Ha-Rishon? Well they probably got it from their great-great-great-great-grandfather עשו.
Eisav. Because by עשו Eisav it says right here בגדי אחיו החמודות,
bigdei achiv ha-chamudot,
the desirous clothes, which are the מדרש Medrash says were the clothes
of אדם הראשון Adam Ha-Rishon that were handed down. Okay, so maybe
so anyway, so they so they put that on their guy on
the top. ומניחין לו בראשו קרקפלו של רבי ישמעאל. U-manichin lo be-rosho
karkaflo shel Rabbi Yishmael.
And they put on his head this sort of the the skull
or the face of... רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael was one of the
martyrs, right? And they, you know, the famous story how they flayed
off like the you know his though the skin from his face.
Okay, so you know all of this is sort of showing that
the
עשו, Eisav, Rome or whatever, you know is dominant over over יעקב.
Yaakov. And
maybe trying to even appropriate, our you know big thing nowadays is
cultural appropriation, right? So they take our beauty, they even took the
head of, you know the face of רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. ותלו
ליה בצואריה מתקל ר' זוזי דפיזא. Ve-talu leh be-tzavarei mitkal reish zuzei
de-piza.
And they put around his neck four hundred... two hundred זוז zuz
according to this גירסא. girsa. But some גירסא girsa say like four
זוז, zuz, I think there's different גירסאות. girsaot. Anyway, a certain amount
of gold because to sort of represent the idea that, you know,
Jews always had to pay this like I think like gold tax
to the Romans. ומחפין את השווקים באונך. U-mechappin et ha-shvakim be-onach. And
they...
and you know they used to say what in America the streets
are paved with gold. So here they paved the marketplaces with onyx.
And
again I don't know exactly yet all the significance of the gold
and of the onyx, but presumably you know that the Romans have
all of the... ומכריזין לפניו umachrizin lefanav
and they have some crier go and announce before him סח קירי
פלסתר, Sach Kiri Plastor, the סח, Sach,
the accounting or the whatever, the calculation of the Rashi says it
means of the great one but Tosafot says it's because they refer
to Yaakov. They wouldn't call Yaakov the great one. So anyway they
say, but whoever it is, either Yaakov or Yitzchak, maybe they recognize
Yitzchak as a great one because Yitzchak was the father of Eisav.
But anyway the calculation of the great one is all a forgery,
meaning that Yaakov sort of prophesied, you know, let me tell you
אחרית הימים acharit hayamim and he prophesied an end of days in
which in which, you know, in which the Jews would be ascendant
and would be triumphant. And they said, yeah, it's all a forgery.
Your great leader, your Yaakov, his his calculation is a forgery, פלסתר
סח קירי פלסתר, Plastor Sach Kiri Plastor, אחוה דמרנא זייפנא, achva demarna
zaifana, the brother of our master,
Eisav is our master, again Rome is Eisav, the brother of our
master is a forger, right? That's Yaakov who basically made a claim
to the בכורה bechora and he's duped our brother Eisav. דחמי חמי,
Dechami chami, whoever gets a chance to see this this parade, this
ritual, this event will see it. ודלא חמי לא חמי, udelo chami
lo chami, if you haven't seen it you'll never see it, because
it's only once every seventy years. So if you missed it, don't
say I'll get it next time around, okay? Because if you missed
it this time you're not going to be around to see it
the next time. Okay, מאי אהני ליה לרמא ברמאותיה? Mai ahani lei
lerama birmautei?
What helped that deceiver in his deceit? Right? This is very obviously
significant, right? Because the whole Yaakov Eisav story does become an anti-semitic
trope about you know the Jews as as deceivers and as schemers
and dishonest. What helped that schemer with his deceit? ולזייפנא בזייפנותיה? Ul'zaifana
b'zaifnutei? And
the and the forger with his forgery? Okay, you know, oh you
Jews, you try to get the better of us, you sneaky scheming
Jews or whatever. In the end, you're in a lowly status and
none of your none of your schemes help you. Okay, ומסיימי בהכי
Umesaymei behachi and this is how they ended: ווי לדין כד יקום
דין. Vay l'den kad yakum den.
But at the end of all of this, they say woe to
this one when the other one arises, like they recognize that all
of this is just to make themselves feel better because at the
end of days the Jews will be ultimately ascendant and then woe
what will happen to us at the end of days. Okay, so
this is like such a great story. Again, I cannot imagine that
maybe there's a tiny kernel of fact that this is based on.
But it's a great story about sort of saying like, here's the
message you're always getting from the outside world. This is the message
you're getting, right? You count for nothing, you're schemers, you're deceivers, we
have the power, we have the wealth, we're on top of you,
we're ascendant. But deep down, they know what it's gonna be at
the end of time. Like even when they're saying all of this
they know at the end we're really, you know, gonna be in
the right. Yeah, Charlie?
By the chronology, first of all Rabbi Yehuda and Shmuel were both
Babylonian Amora'im. Yeah. So they wouldn't have known Roman, right, exactly. But
these would have happened once or two or three times by the
time of the end of Shmuel's life because it was only,
I mean they were only every seventy years.
What was it, two or three times? At most it would have
happened twice. What are you talking about?
So 140, 210, I mean I don't know exactly when Shmuel died.
I know, but he didn't live 140 years.
At most you could have, no I mean he wouldn't have been
around to observe them, but they they didn't happen,
oh I see your point. Okay fine, in the world, got it.
Okay, that's a good point too. Like how often, how often could
it have happened in world history that he could be making this
claim? Yeah. Right. Okay, not only that, if it's the, if it's
the skull of Rabbi Yishmael, right, exactly. What was
that? Like
anyway, moving on. So
the Gemara says like this. Okay, דתנא דידן מאי טעמא לא קחשיב
לה? Detana didan mai ta'ama lo kachashiv lah?
So if that's really one of the pagan holidays, why isn't it
mentioned in our Mishnah? So the Gemara says, דהא דאיתא בכל שתא
ושתא קחשיב, דהא דליתא בכל שתא ושתא לא קחשיב. Deha de'ita bechol
sheta vesheta kachashiv, deha d'leita bechol sheta vesheta lo kachashiv. We're only
mentioning annual ones. We're not mentioning ones that occur only seventy years.
So הני דרומאי? Hani deromai? Now those are the days of the
Romans. דפרסאי מאי? Deparsai mai? How about the Persian holidays? So here
are the names: מוטדרי וטוריסקי מוהרנקי ומוהרין. Mutadri veturiski muhranki umaharin.
Okay, those are the names, הני דפרסאי. Hani deparsai. Those are the
Persian ones. I could tell you what they all mean but then
I'd have to kill you. Okay, הני דפרסאי ודרומאי. Hani deparsai uderomai.
Those are the Persian and the Roman holidays. דבבלאי מאי? Debevlai mai?
How about the Babylonian holidays? מוהרניקי ואכנישי בחנוני ועשרה באדר. Muhraniki veachnishi
bachnuni ve'asara b'adar.
So that one I got, the tenth of Adar. Okay, אמר רב
חנן בר רב חסדא אמר רב, ואמרי לה אמר רב חנן בר
רבא אמר רב: חמש בתי עבודה כוכבים קבועין הן. Amar Rav Chanan
bar Rav Chisda amar Rav, ve'amrei lah amar Rav Chanan bar Rava
amar Rav: chamesh batei avoda kochavim kevuin hen. There are five like
fixed places of idolatry. אלו הן Elu hen and these are they:
בית בעל דבבל. Beit Baal debevel. The house of the temple of
Baal in Bavel; בית נבו בכורסי, Beit Nevo b'Kursi,
the temple of Nevo in Kursi, I don't know where Kursi is;
תרעתא שבמפג, Tar'ata she-be-Mapag,
the gate in Mapag; צריפא שבאשקלון; Tsrifa she-be-Ashkelon; נשרא שבערוביא, Nashra she-be-Arvaya,
and נשרא Nashra in Arabia. See, those are like five major pagan
temples. כי אתא רב דימי ki asa Rav Dimi הוסיפו עליהן, osifu
aleihem, יריד שבעין בכי, Yerid she-be-Ein Bechi, the יריד Yerid like the
marketplace in עין בכי, Ein Bechi, and נצבחא שבעכו. Nazbakha she-be-Akko. All
right, so I don't know why we're mentioning necessarily like temples and
why it matters that they're fixed. We want to know what the
regular and fixed holidays are, but whatever are the temples are the
temples. Anyway, איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri נט בר אושא שבעכו. Nat-bar-Usha she-be-Akko.
Fine. רב דימי מנהרדעי Rav Dimi min Nahardai מתני איפכא: masni ipcha:
יריד שבעכו, Yerid she-be-Akko, נצבחא שבעין בכי. Nazbakha she-be-Ein Bechi. Fine. אמרי
ליה רב חנן בר רב חסדא לרב
חסדא: amrei leh Rav Hanan bar Rav Hisda l'Rav Hisda: מאי קבועין
הן? mai kevuin hen? What does it mean when it says that
they are... that they are fixed? אמר ליה: amar leh: הכי אמר
אבוה דאמך, hachi amar Avuha d'immach, this is what your... the your
your
mother's father said: קבועין הן לעולם, kevuin hen l'olam, תדירא כולי שתא
פלחו להו. tidira kula shata palchu lehu. They are fixed forever, כולי
שתא פלחו להו, kula shata palchu lehu, they are always worshipping in
it throughout the whole... those are the actual pictures of those places,
cool. Okay, they're always doing worship there. All right, so it's not
just maybe on special days, they worship there on a daily
basis they worship. אמר שמואל: amar Shmuel: בגולה אינו אסור אלא יום
אידם בלבד. ba-gola eino asur ela yom edam bilvad.
In exile only the day of the holiday itself is forbidden, not
the others. So that of course allows the days before, it doesn't
explain why the practice was to even do business on the day
of the holiday itself, we've been discussing that since the beginning. Okay,
and the גמרא says: יום אידם נמי מי אסר? yom edam nami
mi asar? What, is the actual day of the holiday itself forbidden?
והא
רב יהודה שרי ליה לרב ברונא לזבוני חמרא, v'ha Rav Yehuda sharei
leh l'Rav Bruna l'zivni chamra, but רב יהודה Rav Yehuda permitted רב
ברונא Rav Bruna to buy wine, ולרב גידל לזבוני חיטין, ul'Rav Giddel
l'zivni chittin, and רב גידל Rav Giddel to buy
wheat, בחגא דטייעי, be-chaga d'atayya, on the holiday of the merchants. So
the גמרא says: No, שאני חגא דטייעי דלא קביעי. shani chaga d'atayya
d'lo kevia. The holiday of the merchants is not a regular annual
holiday. Okay, who cares though? Is it pagan? So רש"י Rashi makes
it sound that also that because it's not regular, maybe it's not
even one that they actually do pagan worship on. But what's really
fascinating is is that it associates, and this is presumably why they
had to forbid it, all of this business, it wasn't just, 'A
holiday happens to be coming, oh, don't do business.' Around the holiday,
all of this business is being done. Everybody's getting ready for the
holiday. So the fact that it mentioned, you know, oh, they're going
to the marketplace and buying wine and wheat on the holiday, right,
you know, and that the nature of the holiday was this merchants'
day, right, the association of these holidays with days of buying and
selling and merchants' days. Oh, and that's actually mentioned the reality that
תוספות Tosafos is dealing with, that Sunday was a major market day
and everybody was doing business on Sunday. Okay, so the problem is
is that the גמרא could say, you know, well, similarly the way
the גמרא said this isn't a pagan holiday, תוספות didn't say Sunday
isn't as important as the other Christian holidays, the גמרא itself actually
identified Sunday already. תוספות has other ways of solving it, you know,
of saying that they're not really they don't really worship עבודה זרה,
avoda zara, other types of things. That's not a trivial thing, that's
a major thing in reframing how we think about Christians and Christianity.
But the other set of answers of תוספות is important because it
draws on why רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael said that it's only the
day itself and not three days before. Why only the day itself?
Why outside of Israel the pagans don't get as excited about their
holidays? You know, three days before is not a big deal, it's
only a big deal in Israel, like there's no logic why they
should be more of a problem in Israel, the pagan days, than
outside of Israel. So if you look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi
says
בגולה, ba-gola, right, two lines before the lines get wide: אין אנו
יכולים להחמיר עצמנו מלישא וליתן עמהם שבניהם אנו יושבים. ein anu yecholim
le-hamir atzmenu mi-lisa u-litain imahem she-beineyhem anu yoshvim.
So first of all, notice also the way that רש"י Rashi now
made it 'we'. He's no longer just describing, right, now maybe he's
saying the 'we' because we as the Jews going back to the
time of שמואל, Shmuel, but it sounds like he's also projecting his
reality. Why is שמואל Shmuel more lenient on the days before outside
of Israel? Because outside of Israel, in Israel we can maybe structure
society more. But outside of Israel we're so deeply embedded within them
that we don't have the luxury of saying 'don't do business for
three days before'. We can't stop our going to work as it
were, we can't stop our normal activities. Like if you're within your
own little echo-chamber culture, right, you can sort of be oblivious about
the larger holidays and, you know, keep on doing business within, you
know, within your little community. But if you're deeply embedded, you can't
just decide three days before every pagan holiday we're going to stop
doing normal types of interactions with them. And then he says: ועוד
משום יראה, ve-od mishum yira, and also because we're afraid that they'll
get angry at us. So this means that the reason שמואל Shmuel
is lenient three days before outside of Israel is not because there's
less of a concern of the paganism. It's because of... it's not
possible to avoid. pose that degree of restrictions. We have to be
more realistic about what it means to be living in this
larger culture, you know, which so anyway so that actually is very
much the reality that the ראשונים Rishonim were drawing on to explaining
often why their practices were not following the practices of the גמרא.
Okay, let's just start by reading the next משנה, Mishnah, just gives
me an opportunity to say one thing about the next משנה. Mishnah.
עיר שיש בה עבודת כוכבים, Ir she-yesh bah avodas kochavim, if a
city has in it idolatry, חוצה לה מותר, chutzah lah mutar,
outside of it is permissible. And היה חוצה לה עבודת כוכבים, hayah
chutzah lah avodas kochavim, if the idolatry was outside of it, תוכה
לה מותר, tochah lah mutar, inside of it is permissible. I'm sorry,
I read it wrong. No, I had it right. No, let's try.
עיר שיש בה עבודת כוכבים, Ir she-yesh bah avodas kochavim, there's idolatry
in the city. חוצה לה מותר, chutzah lah mutar, outside of it
is permissible, it's only forbidden in it. היה חוצה לה עבודת כוכבים,
hayah chutzah lah avodas kochavim, if the idolatry was outside of it,
so תוכה לה מותר tochah lah mutar inside the city is permissible.
Now what is permissible? What are we talking about? Okay, so עבודה
זרה I don't think. Don't do עבודה זרה, no, clearly that's always
forbidden. So the simple reading of this is יש בה עבודת כוכבים
yesh bah avodas kochavim means has a pagan holiday and we've the
whole context is doing business on or before their pagan holidays. So
let's say this town has a pagan holiday, can I go ahead
and do business in the suburbs? You know, is the suburbs considered
to be connected to the town? Or if they're having some pagan
holiday out there in the villages, they're doing some I don't know
agricultural holiday, but they're oblivious about it in the town itself. Can
I go ahead and do business in the town? It says yeah,
sure. It's only forbidden in the region in which the pagan holiday
is taking place. But in the nearby region, even if one is
the suburbs and the other is the town, you're allowed to do
business as long as it's not being celebrated in that place itself.
That is the simple meaning of this משנה. Mishnah. However, רמב"ם Rambam
reads it to say, you ready for this? You're not allowed to
live in a city that has idols, okay?
And or so אסור to live or to enter. You can't live
or enter such a city. And then he says but how about
the fact that we do it? So he similarly echoing like the
line that רש"י Rashi said a minute ago said like what can
we do? God has placed us in exile and we live among
them and we have no choice but to do it. But that
he reads that in principle the משנה Mishnah is actually saying you
shouldn't even be in a city in which there are idols. Now
maybe you could read it in which there's an active day holiday
going on, but if I remember correctly I'd have to check it
I think he actually says this in the פירוש המשניות Perush HaMishnayos
even just the presence of idols you really shouldn't even be in
the city itself. Obviously, then he says of course it's impossible for
us to keep that.
So then does he understand the first משנה Mishnah as like a
בדיעבד? bedi'avad?
Like oh, you mean how would you be doing business three days
before if there's got to be idols in the city to begin
with? Yeah, it's a pretty good point. You're right, I hadn't honestly
made that connection, but you're right. Like so what's the context in
which you're there that you're doing business if there's already, yeah, it's
an excellent point. Yes, Charlie what did you want to say?
There were a lot of Christians in Egypt in his time, more
than there are today.
Well, yeah, he himself sort of acknowledged that. Here, let me read
it to you.
He says,
oh, that's חולין, Chullin, hold on.
Give me
just one second, I know we're already over, but I just really
wanted to share this. Let me see if I can find, where
is the פירוש המשניות של הרמב"ם? Perush HaMishnayos shel ha-Rambam? Come on.
Oh, here we go.
He says like this: לפי שאסור
להיכנס לעיר שיש בה עבודת
כוכבים, lefi she-assur
lehikanes le-ir she-yesh bah avodas
kochavim, כל שכן לדור בה, kol she-ken ladur bah, וכל שכן לסחור
בה. ve-kol she-ken lishor bah. Okay, and he says he says ופיכך
ידוע לך שכל עיר של אומה שהיה להם בית תפלה של עבודת
כוכבים, u-lefichach yadu'a lecha she-kol ir shel umah she-hayah lahem beis tiflah
shel avodas kochavim, בלא ספק אותה עיר
אסור לעבור בה בכוונה.
belo sofek osah ir
assur la'avor bah be-khavanah.
If they have a house of worship of עבודה זרה, you cannot
intentionally go into the city. כל שכן לדור בה. kol she-ken ladur
bah. אבל אנחנו תחת ידיהם, aval anachnu tachat yedeihem, בעוונותינו, ba-avonoseinu, ושוכנים
בארצם, ve-shochnim be-artzam, אנוסים. anusim. We are under their control בעוונותינו ba-avonoseinu
and we're living in their land אנוסים, anusim, we are living here
against our will. ונתקיים בנו מה שנאמר ועבדתם שם אלהים מעשה ידי
אדם. ve-nitkayem banu mah she-ne'emar va-avadtem sham elohim ma'aseh yedei adam. ואם
העיר הדין כן כל שכן דין בית עבודת כוכבים עצמה, ve-im ha-ir
hadin ken kol she-ken din beis avodas kochavim atzmah, שאסור לנו כמעט
לראותה. she-assur lanu kim'at li-osoh.
If this is true about living in the city, how much more
so about about their actual house of worship where it's to a
certain degree even forbidden for us to even look at it. כל
שכן להיכנס בה, kol she-ken lehikanes bah, how much more so to
enter into it. So I thought it would be a little appreciated
like the extreme of that statement which is not the sense you
get in the גמרא at all and רמב"ם Rambam himself acknowledges it's
not possible to do, but he actually understands that what this משנה
Mishnah is saying is that you're not even supposed to be in
such a city. Again, I don't understand, Jonathan makes the excellent point,
so then why do you have to tell me not to do
business if I'm not allowed to even be in the city? Maybe
you're living in a little Jewish village near and it's a holiday,
I don't even know the answer. Anyway, let's finish the משנה Mishnah
because I want to now end us with that in mind, the
end of the משנה, Mishnah, מהו לילך לשם. mahu lalechet lesham. And
this is part of where רמב"ם Rambam gets it. What about going
to the town? So בזמן שהדרך מיוחדת לאותו מקום אסור, bizman shehaderech
meyuchedet leoto makom assur,
if the path only goes into the town and sort of ends
in the town, you can't go to the town.
ואם היה יכול להלך למקום אחר מותר, ve'im hayah yachol lehalach lemakom
acher muttar, you're allowed. So when can you not go into the
town? So רמב"ם Rambam would say don't go into a town that
has idolatry in it, that has the houses of foreign worship. Maybe
you can pass through it if you're just passing through to get
to the other side, but don't even go there temporarily let alone
live there if it has an עבודה זרה in it. That seems
very harsh. Wow. Okay so and non-impossible. So presumably the פשט pshat
of this as we said is not talking about the presence of
an idol but a pagan holiday. And then you can understand it
a little bit more. Here it is, it's not three days before,
it actually is the I
don't know Dionysus's whatever feast is going on, Dionysus's feast is going
on there's revelry, they're doing their pagan worship. I want to enter
into that town on this day. So no, if you live there
it's different. If you live there you're not required to leave the
town on the
holiday, but this is just where you live and all the stuff
that's going on around me. But don't enter it! What are people
going to think? Oh, somebody's going into this town that's having their
Dionysus holiday today. They're going to think you're going to participate. So
that's the simpler read. It's not about idols, it's not about living,
it's about the pagan holiday, doing business in the town or out
of the town, and going into the town, not being in the
town, going into the town on the day that the pagan holiday
is taking place. And then it says if this path is just
you just cut through this town to get somewhere else, it's on
a highway or whatever, people won't assume you're going there to participate.
Even if you are going there to stay there not to participate,
but people who see you on this road they're going to assume
you're just driving through town. Okay but if the road ends in
town and doesn't go through, people are going to assume why else
are you going? All they're thinking about is that today is Dionysus's
feast and they see you going they'll assume you're going to participate.
This raises last thing I want to say, the important question of
are there concerns of מראית עין maris ayin when it looks like
you're going to do something forbidden but not that you're doing something
forbidden? Meaning a classic מראית עין maris ayin is I'm eating something
that looks like a cheeseburger but the cheese is really soy. But
you see me eating it and you say Dov is eating a
cheeseburger. But how about going into McDonald's to use the bathroom or
to buy a Coke?
So you might not give me the benefit of the doubt and
think oh my God he's going in to buy a cheeseburger.
But you're not thinking that the act I'm doing is per se
forbidden. You're thinking I'm going to do something forbidden. Is that מראית
עין? maris ayin? That's an important debate in the ראשונים Rishonim whether
the idea of מראית עין maris ayin applies when you think I'm
going to do something forbidden. So how about this case? You see
somebody going into the town, it's Dionysus's holiday, you think he's going
to go participate. So this would seem to be evidence that there's
a problem of מראית עין maris ayin when it just looks like
you're going to do something forbidden. Now you could say look it's
עבודה זרה, it's a much bigger deal, it's more weighty, we have
a more broader definition. But, and here's the line I want to
leave you with, רבינו יונה Rabbeinu Yonah says no. He says part
of the holiday, it's like think of pilgrimage holidays. He says part
of the practice is the going to the town on the holiday.
Part of the practice is the traveling to the place. Think of
like you're going to Mecca,
the Hajj. That is itself the practice. People who see you going,
if they think you're going because of the holiday they don't just
think you're going to worship and now you're just getting there. The
act of going is itself part of the worship, is itself part
of the practice. Okay? So the case here is don't go to
the town if you're not just passing through or the road isn't
just going straight through, because it looks like you're going to participate
in the holiday. Okay, but the question is how much does that
mean then it's just looking like you're doing something forbidden or is
it like you're planning on doing something forbidden or how much is
it that the act itself is seen as a type of participation
and seen itself as something forbidden. Okay went a little over but...
So the washroom in McDonald's is okay?